Can you have an else if kind of a, like a, you know, vif and then velse, velse if?
Yeah, you absolutely can.
And so, oh, so the question here is regarding can we extend the if else statement?
And absolutely, because when Evan and the team were designing the API for this,
their goal really is to extend upon what you already know.
So if you have if and else, why not else if?
So in this particular case, let's just go ahead and for sake of,
we're going to do the same thing before this time, characterList.length,
and then this time we'll just make it even just to kind of showcase this.
And then otherwise we'll have a p element velse,
that's like there are odd characters, which is a punny joke, ha, ha, ha.
Anyways, so it's even right now.
So we add this now and we add another one.
Let's do appa.
Refresh, boom.
So it'll run through all the scenarios and end up at the last one.
So generally speaking, from a performance perspective,
you do probably want to optimize for your most common scenario at the very top
so you don't have view running through everything.
But otherwise, yeah, you can else if as long as you see fit.
Question here.
I would reach for namespacing characterList under this.
Is there any gotchas with that?
Namespacing the characterList.
Character in this characterList?
This in this character, like down here?
Up in the markup.
Oh, okay.
So you're saying you wanted to namespace this?
Yeah, I would put it under this for like,
because once you get inside character, is character a local variable
or is it on the parent object?
So I tend to put character in this characterList,
meaning it's on the parent component or parent, in this case the app.
Is there any gotchas inside of that?
I see.
Okay, so I'm going to try to understand.
So you're saying that because of the way it's kind of like spelled out,
it's kind of confusing.
So you want to be explicit about where characterList is being called on for the parent?
Yeah, adding this dot.
Oh, this dot.
Okay.
We have avoided that up until this point.
Something that you'll notice is that we're not actually doing anything special
as far as calling the data that's inside of the app, right?
We have this characterList array.
And all we're doing is saying, as you can see here, characterList, character.
We're basically naming things as we go.
And it's because Vue is basically trying to do that step of like abstracting away
the things that you would normally have to define.
So if this were JavaScript, you might have to be like,
oh, I have to call the app.data.characterList to be like, I'm calling characterList.
But Vue knows that basically there are conventions in the way you kind of call things.
So rather than having you explicitly define everything,
it is trying to basically help abstract that away.
But in the future, for those who want to be more explicit,
there are ways to kind of namespace that out a little bit more.
So we'll get into that later on.
Cool.
Go for it.
I mean, you could almost say that characterList is like a global, in a sense,
are global to the app?
Yes.
At this point, yeah.
Especially once we start getting into components,
because components obviously is a big part of frameworks these days,
that will definitely, characterList will become, well, hold on.
Let me backtrack.
So your question here is regarding whether or not characterList
becomes global to the entire app.
And so it is global to the context in that specific rendering context.
So in the case of this page, right, it has the characterList, it can show it.
When we start getting into components, it will have its own scope.
And it will be separate from the parent.
So in that regard, you cannot expect characterList to just show up in any context.
So in Vue, it tries to basically try to optimize for performance.
There's a performance impact when it comes to making things global.
But more importantly, you have namespace polluting that often happens.
And so Vue tries to protect you from that by forcing you to be explicit with what you want
to be shared and what you want to be made global.
So there are ways to make global variables in Vue.
But I would say most of the time, you're probably not doing that.
And there are other ways you're trying to share data.
So even in the instance of, say, the use case regarding, like, a user being logged in,
that's something that impacts a lot of different components.
And so in the past, the first thing you might be, like, tempted to do is say,
well, I'm just going to make a global variable that says, hey, is the user logged in?
Because, I don't know, call it 30% of our code base uses it.
But that also means 70% of your code base doesn't use it.
And now it has this user logged in state that it has to either worry about
or it might conflict for some other reason.
And so Vue 3 in particular, especially with the Composition API and Composables,
which I promise we'll cover in this workshop,
allows you to then segment that to be very explicit that, like,
on the 30% that care about user logged in, great, drop it in.
Otherwise, you don't even have to worry about it.
And so we'll definitely be talking about that.
But does that help to answer your question?
Okay, solid.
Did you have a question?
A small thing.
On your V4, like a first and last equivalent.
So you want to do them in commas, but not on the last person.
AngularJS would be first and last when you're looping those.
Oh, they have the first.
Okay.
So you seem like we wanted to render, like, the list out as, like, a string.
It's a string with commas, but not on your last guy.
Got it.
Okay.
So the question here is around,
if we wanted to actually list the string of characters instead,
that actually, I would say, okay, there's a couple ways we could do this.
With the information we have now,
the V4 actually would probably feel a little bit clunky because,
and let's show this.
So let's go ahead and do this.
So with the information we have here,
if we wanted to have a P element here instead that, say,
took a span of every character in character list,
lists, yep, okay,
then I'm going to do the character.name.
Okay.
So this should just, like, give us a mash of things.
Oop, I did not close it.
Save.
Okay.
Boom.
Right?
But what we need is we need that comma space.
But you're probably also thinking,
oh, okay, let me refresh this now.
Okay.
That looks better.
But to your point, we need the ability to cut off the last part.
And so, gosh, I think the way I would do this at first glance would basically be
I would probably just actually do a, no, I think I would just do another inline.
Using only the techniques we have right now,
I would say we have if character list, or, okay, so we want to pull out,
okay, here's a great example of where we need the index of something, right?
And so I'm going to repeat this a lot because I think this is a core thing
I'd like to see other APIs continue as well,
is that we build on what you already know.
And since we're in a for loop in JavaScript,
we can actually pull the index out by just pulling it out as a second argument
because this is the standard JavaScript API.
So, again, Vue really tries not to, like, come in and, like, reinvent things for you.
Like, once you learn it, it's a convention we know, why not use it?
So then we can go index is equal to character list.length minus one.
And if that is true, empty string, otherwise, comma, like this.
And I, did I slightly do that off?
Ah, I can't spell.
Off by one, once again.
And I'm, oh, autocomplete messed me up.
length, length, length.
This, this, this, this.
Great.
There we go.
So there are ways, though, if, let's say that in your app
that you want to go ahead and do, like,
you're constantly stringing stuff together and you want it to always leave off,
there are ways you can create custom directives
so you could pass it in and it would do something specific.
Most of the time, I think what I've seen people do instead is that
when we talk about computed properties in a little bit,
that's usually something that people use a lot for these sort of, like,
computations, which we'll cover them.
Does that help to answer your question, though?
Yeah.
But you're right.
I think Angular did have some nice, like, syntactic sugar for stuff like that.
So I would say that, absolutely, that is a great callback.